...it's...two thousand fifteen and,
as usual we're going to get to talk about cplus-plus
native code and also something really interesting that we learned about it build
objectives see compiling in visual studio on windows
so without further ado I want to have you guys introduce yourselves and tells little about what
you done related to what I just said okay I'm jim route again I'm
...manager for the cplus-plus compiler we hooked up the
...front-end to compile cplus-plus and objectives
...and targeting the runtime that these guys.
Are going to introduce themselves for...that I am a program manager
...with the windows team and we basically took a lot of the work that
...done and really ran with it and
...speed the equate objective...solution...
today I'm a software engineer and the same team on?
A lot of the implementations...the frameworks and foundation gets.
And,...heard rigorous I'm actually in...not in the product team I take with...
do and I try to help partners use these, you know, their technology to bring their products
...to windows, windows phone most recently candy...
...work...denotes read on absolutely and I was running
it on my windows phone eighty-one device and I didn't realize was actually the ios app at that
point...thanks you guys, yeah, that really work it runs faceted runs it's very
stables very fast...just a great experience school so remember you can ask questions out
there and the topic is compiling objectives
see on windows using visual studio it's also any question you might have
for cplus-plus back and in fact you guys finally.
Solve the guard problem poet out
your optimizations so that's something we can talk about as well so talk really was about
two things it's all the code generation technology that you can get right now in visual
studio twenty fifteen in addition to the...is going-to be coming out what two days after we...
At least at least one bs update cycle later.
So, let's jump right into this what is so it's what's the name
of technology to work on this project island
...island what island...it's a lovely pedestrian bridge somewhere on been
...I believe so we commandeer that name that
...going...because it's a bridge exactly it's a bridget
...way to get cold you've already written that happens to be using objective
see but get that code on to the windows platform now
...is the objected see with the gigantic api underneath so, you know,
core ui coronation
blah-blah-blah so you had to do translation there I hear you've done some interesting things?
To think of it as and implementation of the platform right so
...spent a lot of time implementing you...make sure it all works together nicely and it's not only
likeit we spent a lot of time integrating angle project which is used to implement open
jail on top of directory which was used by the kenny...project and
...inspire able to ship it went so fast and this platform
possum so what
actually is going on underneath that enables that's.
Binary rewriting what's going on so it's not rewriting binary
said it's actually compiling objective secret on
...just implemented the things that they need to be there for at all
to come together nicely so what happens when apple releases and updated you
...sure ...remember the way...development works.
When you're writing your app for ios...sort of these two numbers
...is your target sdk which is, you know, usually the latest version of the os
in the sdk that exists but there's also this other notion called
...base st and that really lets you set the bounds...you say as developer I'm going to
support iowa's versions sixty-eight or fly through eight or something like that so,
most developers to maximize the available market...actually don't set their base sdk to be
eight-point...or eight-point also there's in fact sort of sliding window of time between
...api...released...widely or completely adopted but
...my point was that you're still going to make changes to all of
...is following...train this is a one-point-zero product right now and as we go for...
of work for more and more api...have more features more great compiler features especially?
And, to go back nothing really happens because, for example, can...ios you can do two
or three updates they've done three or four in the last four months or something like that
eight one patched...a lot it doesn't matter right in our case we compile against
unicode we shipment code ios on a separate track and your application
...break or anything like that so you don't have to be on the faster?
And, you get...because
you're compiling and ios and app that was originally designed for ios
...written objective...using all the underneath
technologies you can extended take advantage of say the windows platform word is going
to be running so you could have, you know, I'd like core tama help me play.
Yacht anyway...that's...a very good points are because of the work committee
and have don your compiling objective see using the same code
jan as you are cplus-plus that means you can call functions between objective
c and cplus-plus world without doing sort of ugly...on
...of parameters...just function calls...same thing the other way so,
yeah, you can you can absolutely...on...on being on xbox api all sorts of
itself when you do compile your objective c code in visual studio
you get all of optimization greatness that jim and team
is done including the new guard technology and sort of, you
know, really preventing a series of attacks...that's really important
value-added because one of the biggest things that we focused on indeo in the
...fourteen timeframe which is visual studio twenty fourteen is security so one of the things
we'll be able to do is wools we suppliers sweats?
It'll basically...a lot of the control flow and
...it and we modify the operating system the os loader the
linger in the compiler for this and it'll all be available in the objective
c code that we generate and,
we really plan to take that forward aggressively
...that we've shipped garden we've got security as part of the product
awesome...so we got questions keep asking them maroon wants to
...ios capabilities might keep changing
...cable keep getting updated we sort of already talked about I plan to keep windows update run
those absentee capabilities wellsort of talk, yeah, we talk about a little bit but I do again
what remind people that look if you want to take advantage of some crazy
to functionality we have a great windows universal api surface you can call right into that and,
interoperate with the rest of your application excellent of
...keying what about swift.
What about swift...is rewarded as well you we are not making any enhancements
in are not moi?
Today as writing I agree completely I do recommend people watts jim
stocked ohm ogg at that slide.
But, no, announcements I'm just playing I'm kidding but you do
...the...front-end.
Right, yeah,
we do point so...now since we want to actually get full fidelity
at the cplus-plus level because that's truly across platform play across vendors
and then we want ctwo at the bottom because that's a cross-platform display within the all
...we have...for the windows platform so since you have
...hooked up to rc to code generator you naturally get objective say
...front-end world parse objectives
...read so papon wants to know.
First walls...great step forward it definitely is my question is
...to recompile any ios...c code windows
...anything get lost in translation also how about you why yet
...we do support you likeit that is to say it's absolutely perfect...every part of you
I can't but we have a pretty good support for most of what people use for your
because we have take every pragmatic approach to implementing the frameworks that people
years what happens is...workflow is we take apps and we make the more and when you do this
...enough apps income stuff works because we
...surface area for testing right and
nothing's really lost in translation because we're not really we're not really translating thing
we're just implementing things that people with people rely on and
are compiler is planning it's exactly what everyone's used to
just have it's a different a...encode generators is different and in fact it's a very
strict strong...and can give us everything for debugging
...visual studio that developers want will look...I don't know but I know himmy uses
x code we...apps is also developer I've tried to put around that's
good I much prefer visual studio and not just because I work at microsoft it's
...it's a great id it's a great experience...a developer so I think what
...little...through the business man I'm just getting your not the...you look like
...yes as?
A so what do you think
...in terms of light the pattern of behavior is going to be...amongst
developers when it comes to using this technology I mean and ios guide.
...apps...whatever I only kind
of focus on ios but now I might want to take a look at windows.
But, it's still going to be a conceptual shift to cover windows...visual studio
...windows and then how do you see this workflow like what's, what's going to happen out with
...stuff...let's let me get that in...as one add something very obviously to what jordan
said of the questions we get pretty often is around performance and I think a
side effect of what we've been saying today is that there's no?
Strict reason why anything you
rights using...on windows will be any slower than intricate cplus-plus.
Or the equivalent code running on equivalent hardware on and
...through important point yes is medical there's no translation there's,
there's already ambition there's no vm there's no emulator...running against the
...of the hardware...an incredible compiler optimization
...your question so I will inversions?
As...guys all...to be long-winded I think what I was saying
was what do you envision the workflow be yes that's right what's the climate you've left.
...and, I play or if we had a few partners play with it, you know, some
...kingett etc or some you know, that we have...here
than what we see is that this is a really great web people to get started out, you know,
he was an interesting exercise where they could state all now we think...too much work they had what
it to android article was portable but they had already done a lot of work in order to make it...portable so,
they...they...thinking it's too much works too much work and we show them
...technology and said okay that's worth a shot right and then we did
they were like okay this is great and as you saw from keynote they're not going to do a lot more
apps and they're like okay now we understand the platform now we know we can do you know,
it's open gl so they can also use angle natively so they're like okay we're going to start moving towards
...natick path but they would have never tried it and they not had this technology to get them
they're very quickly they got there they saw the users the staff and platform
dioxide monetize and they were like okay that that's...so for
us know in vandalism this is a really great way to get people smart people see it and they're
like that makes...easier now I expect...be some people that...will keep,
you know, what
...and they'll be other people that say we'll novel native ask me dive into their next generation apps
...the that as they do more and whereas that's a perfect way to get started because we do one
after the native when you bring your...apps...still...think
...live tiled some local modifications we do in...for-you lab we
...this api somatic seamless for you to do it but there's a lot of other features right
...out there's a lot of other features we want people take advantage off and do
...on cplus-plus right now it's transparent you can just start
...seamless right so we wanted to you...to take advantage...an as you go through
it at some point you make the decision of...on...out of these do is
we want to make it...I think of...your...the talk the demo really lit up
...language services we didn't get a chance really...
Language services but you really did depth...colors asia and
...handful language services to do...continue completely...model...jump
...it's I mean visual studio is a great idea and we've just made a great for visual for
objectively as well...and ctwo is a great back-end compiler...credit
that's...as well as...compile we have a great team the team
isn't as an amazing team for code generation and for security and those two things together I think
...big deal but I think the
...going back to your point the integration with visual studio is really powerful
...makes it extremely low...to move to use them.
So, we have a question which I think when phone as...
design but how do we get ios apps to this experience metro tiles etc?
Well, it's just...talked about before games it seamless...because...to be
consistent across platforms like game looks the exact same whether it's unity or you know,
these technology or any other technology the games are like the exact same
influence across-the-board so there there's no ...patterns of with regards to you...kid they've
...they have right now it does look a little bit ios
...something that...have to look at with
...should be theme and what is the best practices...right now because we're just getting started
...sorry control and they're making those decisions as they go with regards to how part I want to go and
...so, are...which will be there...luminaries to should not be
are problem-solves so it is also if you are and iowa's developer you
can already theme...your you like it...you can say I want my buttons to be yellows of
...that's absolutely within your control and ...got a little bit in
the demo we did earlier today about how we can...customize
look and feel of various...elements by default without you having to actually do anything
and another example of that is we can offer support automatic support for
back button integration so if you're if you're app uses a standard
...navigation controller and...do nothing else we can automatically
...physical backpacking support onto...backwards navigation so
we've done a lot of this work for you to make it really easy but you can also customize
the mcallen as austin tx and of course?
Ios is models...right
...flatten so at least there's some work you don't have to do you.
Will there be a windows emulator for ios I think that's a legal problem
...of technical probable there's no reason to do the...because
...compiling directly and regenerating code directly to the run-time just like we
would compile cplus-plus so you can view your application running on windows as a exactly
...important emphasize...it's a windows application
we can pilot just as we would any other application on windows...so happens
...now the going back to the workflow sort of question was if
...and ios developer?
And, I had always been drooling
and watching visual studio and jealous of my friends...music and I know job
...the same so my point is I think I'm trying to.
And, I forgot...
what happens ej bourbon late at night...to...we do have support for
...visual studio we...some time in like incorporating
...complete support...like when you press dot what happens and playing
has an api that actually were able to leverage for to great effect for
forgetting information about what could happen in that context and we had a lot of success with that
and at also allowed us to navigate through the code right when you say
like this token I'm interested in what this says like show me the definition of what the...
or...all these things are made possible by...being a very useful
products and I guess so going back to was trying to...
I'm talking about going from windows to...ios device so right
now what we have is taking existing ios and bring it to windows but
from a developers perspective I'm talking about the experience of writing code
in visual studio and getting really nice design-time that all
...cross-platform story there's talk here about and,
the idea is that you can write for android ios
or windows directly and if you can compile out
...onto the metals so to speak for objective
see you can stay within visual studio
on windows doing your cross complaint cross-platform development until you're ready
to deploy one last build would actually go through the...to get your onto the
iowa's store so that would be but that would just be copying all your source
code all your files bringing it over to x code compiling building
optimizing there will we the point right expectations that people generate
visual studio projects for it and check those projects into...source repository so they can make
modifications how are they like in visual studio and then when they pull on their
...computer yes they can just build...next node n
continue got so that goes the through...emulator question right you're not going
to be deploying to...ios device from windows because that's illegal or maybe that's
not the reason it's not the problem we're trying to solve the problem trying to solve is to help people
right great windows application and not just games himmy sorry...just
games null not all is a lot outside...now what about what is interesting because when you
say not just games as himmy mention games are really self-contained
...easier problem somerset but when you have
an app that's like very platform?
You know, ties into a bunch of the api that the hardware supports how does
that work when I want to bring...of...you said you've done a lot of work yes...so
...if we if we step back and just keep reminding ourselves that you are writing a windows
app you're just using objective see for certain bits and bobs of that
application...now you can imagine all sorts of permutations?
Stem from that you could imagine writing your ui using
...but keeping some of the back-end logic, you know, just
...fancy networking...really proud of it really works well...be objectives you can bring that and you can link the
two together you can go the other way you could have your you are using objective...and you could have all the
back-end windows...custom staffin csharp or cplus-plus
and you can tie all these things together so you're not you're not limited you're not writing inside
...sandbox are not limited to certain...objective see compatible api you have you are
writing windows application...I could have objected see under-age...five.
...as of universal windows app.
Someday technically,
technically you could...because...adaptor winner...the middle...from and html
...but that's the beauty of the avi...that's why we worked so hard...badly and you can certainly
invoke web views within the context of either and objectives the ios you likeit,
for example, application...
there are no questions which I find really unbelievable this is channel my...
But, so, now you're stuck with me...but.
Let's continue to talk one of the questions I have...I really...curious about
...engineering perspective what was...hard was this
...we don't sell them seldom would really think about the and how much time did you spend
on this...fortunately a lot
...hard problem a lot of the really hard problems I should say we sort of outsourced to...
We made a few large stones...getting moi.
Not to say...was trivial at all no it's
a very large very complicated project and...
they reach out and actually say thanks to shane...who actually worked weekends
we started really I would say like around christmas time wow so it really,
really is a major accomplishment...all working...really proud of...I think it's going to be a great
products we have a ways to go we really want to make sure everybody understands that we really do
...and...you assad to look at it have at least for
...because what when I look at what we have today with regards to out syntax
...highlighting a lot of the...the bagging and all that like literally right here
where you have is james dean doing some first of all we had a rocking
...that we started with...gives...came in and said okay, yeah, we're going to bring all the...
compilers all that stuff but we were building on top of visual studios so all of the
...the taj all those things where there right so they did some really hard work
in a very short time if you look at how much they accomplished, you know,
it's not that long...out but it's because they were building on top of
a very strong foundation...to use extremely extensible it's very flexible and,
do like literally I would see that yeah, we're going to get syntax highlighting next week...any
which is like all like it's mind-boggling to thing they could do it thanks bye-bye now
...for the language syntax ...asia...what's your
point of even on the or even but outside the work ...
have done our team has put...a ton of work to make sure that experience is really,
really perform...really, really compatible so when you schools through through ui you're not going
to get lags and jitter and that sort of thing things are going
to run really well really fascinating to look great and the only doer to
...demos and everything so everything being map it onto the act...everything was really,
really quick?
This early on right so I think the only thing we really need to
worry about from down to one this goes out is really stress testing everything
...that we really, really optimize and we get the right security attributes encodes what
...you are right mass so thank you for asking questions to
...want to know...see access...a wind thirty-two or only when
...you are...windows application whatever you can call from a windows out
...objectives the is you can access both native see out that's how
...runtime implemented and,
then...because again we have the avi so you...david want to know
are you worried about apple having a negative reaction to the release of this product I
think so-called...across platforms has been at...since probably the first programming languages
...and that's really what we're talking about...reusing your code
your the developer and what you do with your code is your business it's yours you wrote?
Clank compiler...has like that say there's nothing beats beyond,
beyond that there's nothing in there to...can come back and say here's we have you implemented...api
is,...like, you know, that's all right we have the submit that but then it's got a buttery about
...vast so there's not much that you can go out there right and,
again,...been on the market for probably five six months now, yeah,
they were before holidays so you know,...one of those things that we're not I think they do
...has been done people can common try
the technologies and I hope we can all collaborate because these makes it better for everybody apps so you know,
hopefully everybody will be happy.
...can you...csharp bs check and...poland makin compile native?
...again slow-motion moi.
So,...songwriter csharp in visual studio...into...and compile
...so maybe if you...about summary think he's talking about the
...also...would have a...talk and now.
Can apple...this out using visual studio code now
...it right now we're just announcing support for visual studio
twenty-fifth gap me visual studio code to be clear is really
a text editor that supports a couple languages with...you know,
deeper model so debugging and?
Can apple...this out actually visual studio code already
...what...see features are available which
objective see features are available name them which ones aren't probably
...much...up with...we support everything
...we have...support through the runtime in the code generation everything...that works just fine
we it just works that's a value prop right we are a...way at
locks all of...and that's like classes and functions those rn like
...foundation as and but I mean...see the language you
have the clank finance exactly there is that's not really a question, yeah,
...we with tessa particularly with planks code...for
...absolutely...lately and it works very beautiful censors
notifications they do a lot of mapping...that you would think of...there because,
for example, notifications...api that you think about
...platform specific local notification gets mapped automatically
...purchases another one that they map automatically so they actually
...later listen to those api implemented natively and you can use
...existing code without having to go there so there's a lot implemented their
...want to know does it doesn't mean it is now possible
report react needed to windows...I don't want to make promises are comments about
...I haven't seen yet tenacity...
Maybe.
Is that...answer I gradients assures online...we...go to
...slash island woodside...cumulative...right on
and follow blog if it doesn't work that's the right answer can you explain something about the candy
crush game that was mentioned was the current windows phone...version
created with this tooling or is this a upfront upcoming phone version?
So, for can...we did it for windows phone aid is
I hey let's go try it out let's make sure this technology works going forward app all they
knew ...the new language stuff we've done...going forward we want to focus...ten but can the
...windows phone ages because app...tried out and we wanted for the holidays and
there wasn't going to be a windows stanford holidays so that's what we did great populate too
much they're I mean it's such a weird game and the people behind it
or they're pretty brilliant it's a couple billion-dollar frenchie so I'm not going to
arguebetween...laughing to the...absolutely can I...windows app and
objectives...not porting just writing native...see instead of
...csharp gaps...that's real story the again reduce compile top-to-bottom
...to the code that runs...with their run-time just like you would write a cplus-plus up
...can you can go into visual studio you can go file new file
...are sorry of addicts add new item make a dot and file
...town from their absolutely but I guess the other way to think about us questions
what he's really asking file new universal
windows that underneath objectives see and I right the whole thing and objectives
...we actually do have that behaviors well actually one of the last things before we came here was one of our
...template I guess,
yeah, it's a visual studio template to create and app that subjective see exactly what you're
...you can just press a button and get a bare-bones object to see project so now I
have to say this I my own personal biases I think objective ce is
...ugly sizzling of...see...like
a small talk maybe you've got this is an insane language?
...it's nice
...that the strict superset epsy it's nice from that perspective.
But, here that people are used...not...like
there's scientific data says the to...you know, keys...your keyboard
...the brackets so-if you want-to even it out go...cone some, you know,
once a year for a week and...it out enough that you'll be even for
...year and I'm a real fan of objective...I actually like it a lot of the...ask
...but out...answer...beat the cold people tend to
love the most is the stuff they've...right and if it already written...and it's
...it's beautiful to them then that's the called really want to help in...okay,
yeah, absolutely that's well-served but isn't there sort of
a cognitive mismatch between the way that you compose
and objective see if you're coming at it from see
even see you spend all your targets the subject isn't it like a conceptual...
strange that's still an object-oriented language just like cplus-plus and it's a strict in
an office of formal superset of cplus-plus but it's definitely a of c so I think that
...at keeping in the theme of everything that we're supposed to be striving for windows
tanned word almost language agnostic we really don't we're not religious about it
...languages whatever you...will generate the code for it that's what we're trying to do fortunes
...for anything on windows great and...need to wrap up the most important thing is that we do love
objective...visual studio love object dasi windows love...see,
come on, over and rights maps for windows
...favorite language rock-and-roll thanks for coming on thank you thank you.